<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A speach deliuered, to the Kings most excellent Maiestie in the name of the sheriffes of London and Middlesex. By Maister Richard Martin of the Middle Temple</title>
            <author>Martin, Richard, 1570-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17510</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112363</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847617</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847617</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12657</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07106)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12657)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1027:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A speach deliuered, to the Kings most excellent Maiestie in the name of the sheriffes of London and Middlesex. By Maister Richard Martin of the Middle Temple</title>
                  <author>Martin, Richard, 1570-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by R. Read] for Thomas Thorppe, and are to be sould by William Aspley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Maister Martins speach to the Kings Maiestie.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last two leaves are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1603-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12657:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12657:1"/>
            <p>A SPEACH DELIVERED, TO THE KINGS MOST <hi>EXCELLENT</hi> MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IESTIE IN THE NAME OF THE SHERIFFES <hi>OF LONDON AND</hi> MIDDLESEX.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Maiſter</hi> Richard Martin <hi>of the Middle Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON Imprinted for <hi>Thomas Thorppe,</hi> and are to be ſould by <hi>William Aſpley.</hi> 1603.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:12657:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12657:2"/>
            <head>A SPEACH DELIVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RED, <hi>TO THE KINGS</hi> MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTIE, <hi>AT HIS NEERE APPROACH</hi> TO LONDON, IN THE NAME <hi>OF THE SHERIFFS OF</hi> LONDON AND MID<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DLE SEX.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He common feares &amp; difficulties which perplex moſt confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Orators, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king before Princes, would more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found my diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſpirit ſpeaking to your high Maieſtie (moſt mighty King &amp; our dreade ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord) did I not know that the meſſage which I bring is to a good
<pb facs="tcp:12657:3"/>
King alwayes gratefull. Curioſity of wit and and affected ſtraines of Oratory I leaue to thoſe, who more delight to tickle the Princes eare, then ſatisfie his deeper iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>To me (moſt gracious Soueraigne) your Maieſties mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſubiect, vouchſafe your milde and Princely attention, whiles in the names of theſe graue Maieſtrates (your Maieſties faithfull Sheriffes of London and Middle SeX) I offer to your benigne grace that loyall and harty welcome, which from that Honorable and ancient Cittie (the heart of this kingdome) is brought by them, whoſe deepe and inward griefe, conceaued for the loſſe of our Peereleſſe and renouned Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> is turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to exceſsiue ioy, for the approach of your excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, by whom the long and bleſſed peace of fiue and forty yeeres is made perpetuall. Great is thac'knowledgement we owe to the memory of our late Princes gouernement, whoſe far ſpread fame, as it ſhall liue reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for euer, ſo of her flouriſhing raigne no other teſtimony neede be required, then that of your high Maieſtie (ſince none can be more honourable) that the like hath not beene read or heard of in our dayes, or ſince the raigne of great <hi>Auguſtus:</hi> So that, euen glorious and victorious Kings haue iuſt cauſe, to enuy the glory and virtue of a woman. But ſhe is gathered in peace to her fathers, a memorable inſtance of your Maieſties diuine obſeruation, that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces differ not in ſtuffe, but in vſe from common men.</p>
            <p>Out of the Aſhes of this <hi>Phenix</hi> wert thou King
<pb facs="tcp:12657:3"/>
               <hi>Iames</hi> borne for our good, the bright ſtarre of the North, to which all true adamantine harts had long before tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned themſelues. Whoſe fame (like a new Sunne ryſing) diſperſed thoſe cloudes of feare, which either our politicke friendes, or open enimies, or the vnnaturall factors for the fift <hi>Monarchy,</hi> had giuen vs ſome cauſe to apprehend: yea our nobility, Councellors, and Commons (whoſe wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and fidellity is therefore renouned as farre as this Iland is ſpoken of) with a generall zeale poaſted to your Maieſties ſubiection: not more incited heere vnto by the right of your Maieſties diſcent &amp; royall bloud, drawen to this faire inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce from the loynes of our ancient Kings; then enflamed with the fame of your Princely and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent virtues, wherewith (as a rich Cabinet with precious iewels) your Kingly minde is furniſhed, if conſtant fame haue deliuered vs a true inuentory of your rare qualities. A King whoſe youth needes no excuſe, and whoſe affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are ſubdued to his reaſon: A King which not onely does iuſtice, (which euen Tyrants doe ſome times) but loues iustice; which habit none but vertuous Princes can put on. Who (immitating the free bounty of the King of Kings) inuites all diſtreſſed people to come vnto him, not permitting <hi>Gehaezie</hi> to take talents of ſiluer, nor change of garments.</p>
            <p>In ſome Princes (my Soueraigne Lord) it is inough that they be not euill, but from your Maieſty wee looke for an admirable goodneſſe, and particular redreſſe, ſo ſtrange an expectation (forerunning your Maiesties comming) hath
<pb facs="tcp:12657:4"/>
inueſted the mindes, of good men with comfort, of bad with feare.</p>
            <p>And ſee how bounteous heauen hath aſsined foure king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, as proper ſubiects for your Maieſties foure Kingly vertues. <hi>Scotland</hi> hath tried your prudence, in reducing thoſe things to order in the Church and Common-wealth, which the tumultuous times of your Maieſties infancie had there put out of ſquare. <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhall require your iuſtice, which the miſeries (I dare not ſay the pollicies) of ciuil wars haue there defaced. <hi>France</hi> ſhall prooue your fortitude, when neceſſary reaſon of ſtate ſhall bend your Maieſties Counſelles to that enterprize. But let <hi>England</hi> be the ſchoole, wherein your Maieſty will practize your tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and moderation: for here flattery will eſſay to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, or force your Maieſties ſtrongeſt conſtancie and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity: baſe aſſentation the bane of virtuous Princes, which (like <hi>Lazarus</hi> dogs) licks euen the Princes ſoares, a vice made ſo familiar to this age by long vſe, that euen Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits are not free from that kinde of treaſon? A treaſon I may iuſtly call it moſt capitall, to poyſon the fountaine of wiſedome and iuſtice, whereat ſo many kingdomes muſt be refreſhed,</p>
            <p>Nor can I be iuſtly blamed, to lay open to a moſt skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and faithfull Phiſition our true griefes, nay it ſhall bee the comfort of mine age, to haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the truth to my Lord the King, and with a hart as true to your Maieſtie as your owne, to make knowne to an vncorrupted King, the hopes and deſires of his beſt ſubiects.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12657:4"/>Who (as if your Maieſtie were ſent downe from Heauen to reduce the golden age) haue now aſſured themſelues, that this <hi>Iland</hi> (by ſtrange working and reuolution now vnited to your Maieſties obedience) ſhall neuer feare the miſchiefes and miſgouernments, which other countries and other times haue felt.</p>
            <p>Oppreſſion ſhall not be here the badge of authoritie, nor inſolence the marke of greatneſſe. The people ſhall euery one ſit vnder his owne Oliue tree, and anoynt himſelfe with the fat thereof, his face not grinded with extorted ſutes, nor his marrow ſuckt with moſt odious and vniuſt Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polies. Vnconcionable Lawiers, and greedie officers, ſhall no longer ſpinne out the poore mans cauſe in length to his vndoing, and the delay of iuſtice. No more ſhall bribes blinde the eyes of the wiſe, nor gold be reputed the common meaſure of mens worthineſſe: Adulterate gold, which can guild a rotten poſt, make <hi>Balam</hi> a Byſhoppe, and <hi>Iſachar</hi> as worthy of a iudiciall chaire as <hi>Solomon,</hi> where he may wickedly ſell that iuſtice, which he corruptly bought. The money changers and ſellers of <hi>Doues,</hi> (I meane thoſe which trafique the liuings of ſimple and religious paſtors) ſhall your Maieſtie whip out of the Temple and common wealth: For no more ſhall Church liuings be pared to the quicke, forcing ambicious Church-men (pertakers of this Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) to enter in at the window by ſimonie and corruption, which they muſt afterwards repaire with vſurie, and make vpp with pluralities.</p>
            <p>The Ports and Hauens of theſe kingdomes which haue
<pb facs="tcp:12657:5"/>
long beene barrd, ſhall now open the mouthes of there ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and the armes of there ſeas, to the gentle amity and iuſt trafficke of all nations, waſhing away our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of vniuerſall pirats, and ſea-wolues, and deryuing (by the exchange of home-bred commodities with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne) into the vaines of this land, that wholeſome blood and well gotte treaſure, which ſhall ſtrengthen the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news of your Maieſties kingdomes. The neglected (and almoſt worne out) nobility ſhall now (as bright Dyamonds and burning Carbunckles) adorne your Kingly Diadem. The too much contemned Clergy, ſhall hang as a precious earing at your Princly eare, your Maieſty ſtill lyſtning to their holy Councels. The wearied Commons ſhall be worne as a rich ring on your royall finger, which your Maieſty with a watchfull eye will ſtill gratiouſly looke vpon. For we haue now a King that will heare with his owne eares, ſee with his own eyes, and be euer iealous of any great truſt, which (being afterwardes become neceſſary) may be abuſed to an vnlymmitted power.</p>
            <p>O my gracious Leige, let neuer any wrye Councels dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert or puddle the fayre ſtreame of your naturall good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Let wicked vſurpers ſeeke lewd arts, to mayntaine their lewd purchaſes: To your Maieſty (called to this Empyre by the conſent of God and men, and now King of ſo many faithfull harts) plaine and dyrect vertue is the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt pollicy, and loue to them, who haue ſhewne ſuch loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to you, is a wall of braſſe.</p>
            <p>They meane to ſell the King to his ſubiects at their owne
<pb facs="tcp:12657:5"/>
price, and abuſe th'authority of his maieſty to their priuate gayne, &amp; greatnes, who perſwade him, that to ſhut himſelfe vp from the acceſſe of his people, is the meanes to augment his ſtate.</p>
            <p>Let me not ſeeme tedious to your Maieſty (my gracious Soueraigne) nor yet preſumptuous, for I counſell not. But whiles your Maieſty hath bin (perchance) wearied with the complaints and inſinnuations of perticulars, for pryuate reſpects; let it be lawfull (my leige) for a hart free from feare or hope, to ſhew your Maiestie the agues which keepe lowe this great body, whereof your Maieſty is the ſound-head.</p>
            <p>Nor are we fed with hopes of redreſſe by immagination (as hungry men with a painted banquet) but by aſſurance of certaine knowledge, drawne out of the obſeruation of your Maieſties forepast actions, and ſome bookes now freſh in euery mans hands, beeing (to vſe your Maieſties owne wordes) the <hi>Viue ideas</hi> or repreſentations of the minde. Whoſe excellent wholeſome rules your Maieſty will neuer tranſgreſſe, hauing bound your Princely ſonne by ſuch heauy penalties, to obſerue them after you, nor dooth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiſeman wiſh, or good man deſire, that your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty ſhould followe other Counſelles or examples then your owne, by which your Maieſtye is ſoe neerelye bound.</p>
            <p>To conclude therefore, what great cauſe haue we to wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to the territories of our Cittie your moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, who (to make vs the glorious and happie head of this
<pb facs="tcp:12657:6"/>
Iland) haue by your fyrſt entrance brought vs th'addition of another kingdome, which warre could neuer ſubdue. So your Maieſties vpright gouernment, ſhall make vs partakers of that felicitie, which diuine <hi>Plato</hi> did onely apprehend but neuer ſee, <hi>(whoſe king is a Philoſopher a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher beeing our King)</hi> Receiue then (moſt gracious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne) that loyall welcome, which our Cittie ſendeth out to meete your Maieſtie; our Cittie which for the long tryall of her loyaltie, obedience, and faithfull readineſſe in all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, your maieſties royall progenitors haue honoured with the title of their Chamber: whoſe faythfull Citizens, with true and well approued harts, humbly lay at your roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all feete their goods and liues, which they will ſacrifice for your maieſties ſeruice and defence, with longing eyes, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to receiue your Maieſtie within their walles, whom they haue long ſince lodged in their harts: praying to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that your Maieſties perſon may be free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> practize, your ſoule ſafe from flaterie, your life extended to the poſſibilitie of nature: and that if not your naturall life, yet your royall line may haue one period with tbe world, your princely ofſpring ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon the throne of their fathers for euermore. And we your Maieſties faythfull ſeruants, humbly ſurrendring into your Maieſties hands that authority, which we holde from you, wiſhing from our harts that all plagues may purſue his poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity, that but conſpires your Maiſties daunger.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12657:6"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
